A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23 FA295
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
1920-1943
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA295
3.52 Cubic Feet 8 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in two subseries:
Subseries 1 - Legal Research Committee Administrative Files
Subseries 2 - Legal Research Projects
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Scope and Contents note
One of the earliest programs of the Commonwealth Fund was the Legal Research Program, which began with the organization of the Legal Research Committee in 1920. The Committee divided into two subcommittees in 1921, one which specialized in the study of administrative law, and the other studied possible reforms in the law of evidence.
The first subcommittee investigated the use of "administrative instruments in the enforcement of legislative policy... the legal issues involved in their powers and the relation of their powers to the traditional system of Anglo-American law." Two types of broad studies were instituted; the first dealt with administrative powers and their use, the other with specific illustrations of such use drawn from the experience of administrative agencies set up by the federal government and other agencies. Several monographs were published based on the research completed by the subcommittee.
The second original subcommittee analyzed the law of evidence and arranged for a number of fact-finding studies which were published in various university law journals. This subcommittee also issued a report in 1927. In addition to funding legal research on current topics, the Committee also provided support for research in legal history and international law, and made special grants available to professors at Oxford University, Yale University, the Foundation for Research in Legal History at the Columbia University School of Law, Harvard Law School, and the University of Chicago School of Law.
The Commonwealth Fund withdrew its support of legal research in 1943, and the Legal Research Committee was discontinued. A card file index to topics and individuals associated with the Legal Research Program is available. Additional documentation concerning the studies published for the Legal Research Committee is located in the records of the Commonwealth Fund's Division of Publications.
Prominent members of the Legal Research Committee include Henry M. Bates, Charles C. Burlingham, Benjamin N. Cardozo, Grenville Clark, James Parker Hall, Learned Hand, Charles F. Hughes, John C. Milburn, George Welwood Murray, Thomas I. Parkinson, Roscoe Pound, Austin W. Scott, Young B. Smith, and Harlan F. Stone.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Law; Legal issues; Legal research; Medical education; Child psychology; Child welfare; Education, Rural; Hygiene; Public health; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; War relief; United States; Public welfare; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Yale University; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Phillips Exeter Academy; Columbia University; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Harvard University; Social Science Research Council; Harkness, Charles W.
- Legal Research Committee Administrative Files, 1; 4 box(es)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - James P. Hall, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - James P. Hall, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - James P. Hall, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, September-December, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chairman's Correspondence and Memoranda - George W. Murray, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Committee on the Establishment of a Permanent Organization for the Improvement of Law - Correspondence, Memoranda and Minutes, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Executive Committee - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1921-1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General Notices to Members, 1921-1927 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General Program Files, 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General Program Files, 1922-1928 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - History of English Law - Correspondence, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Interoffice Memoranda, 1924-1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Members' Correspondence - Henry M. Bates, 1928-1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Members' Correspondence - Henry M. Bates, 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Members' Correspondence - Charles C. Burlingham, 1921-1944 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Members' Correspondence - Benjamin N. Cardozo, 1921-1936 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Members' Correspondence - Grenville Clark, 1931-1943 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Members' Correspondence - Learned Hand, 1930-1944 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Members' Correspondence - Charles E. Hughes, 1926-1936 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Members' Correspondence - John G. Milburn, 1920-1930 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Members' Correspondence - Thomas I. Parkinson, 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Members' Correspondence - Roscoe Pound, 1920-1927 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Members' Correspondence - Roscoe Pound, 1928-1937 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Members' Correspondence - Austin W. Scott, 1937-1943 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Members' Correspondence - Young B. Smith, 1928-1943 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Members' Correspondence - Harlan F. Stone, 1920-1936 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Minutes and Reports, 1920-1940 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws Correspondence and Reports, 1923-1927 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Publishers' Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Scope and Contents note
    University of Chicago, June 2, 1927-September 12, 1927 Yale University, November 26, 1923-October 24, 1930
  - Reports, 1920-1928 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Reports, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Reports, 1932-1934 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Reports, 1935-1943 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Research Proposals (Adams to Moore), 1920-1925 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Research Proposals (Morgan to Workingmen's), 1920-1925 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Research Proposals (Blackburn to Yale), 1927 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Research Proposals (Boston University to California), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Research Proposals (Colorado to Minnesota), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Research Proposals (Montana to Yale), 1928 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Research Proposals (Administration to Columbia), 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Research Proposals (Committee to Cornell), 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Research Proposals (Finch to Harvard), 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Research Proposals (Johns Hopkins University), 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Research Proposals (Legal to National), 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Research Proposals (Ploscowe to Wisconsin), 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Research Proposals (American to Futrell), 1935-1946 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Research Proposals (Graubart to State), 1935-1946 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Research Proposals (United to Yale), 1935-1946 (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Legal Research Projects, 2; 4 box(es)
  Arrangement note
  This subseries is arranged in three parts:
  Part 1 - Administrative Law and Practice
  Part 2 - International Law
  Part 3 - Law of Evidence
  - Administrative Law and Practice, 1
    - Administrative Powers and Methods of the Department of Agriculture - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1928-1930 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Administrative Powers and Methods of the Department of Agriculture - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1931-1935 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Administrative Powers and Methods of the Department of Agriculture - Financial Data, 1929-1932 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Blue Sky Laws - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1932-1951 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Blue Sky Laws - Financial Data, 1932-1940 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Columbia University - American Legal History - Foundation for Research in Legal History (Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda), 1930-1932 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Columbia University - American Legal History - Foundation for Research in Legal History (Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda), 1933-1936 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Columbia University - American Legal History - Foundation for Research in Legal History (Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda), 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Columbia University - American Legal History - Foundation for Research in Legal History (Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda), 1941-1950 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Columbia University - Control of Business in Medieval and Tudor England (Correspondence, Finances, and Memoranda), 1934-1936 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Columbia University - Control of Business in Medieval and Tudor England (Correspondence, Finances, and Memoranda), 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Columbia University - Growth and Effect of Administrative Boards in the United States (Correspondence and Memoranda), 1934-1942 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Columbia University - Growth and Effect of Administrative Boards in the United States (Financial Data), 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Federal Trade Commission Study - General Correspondence and Memoranda, 1922-1924 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Federal Trade Commission Study - General Correspondence and Memoranda, 1924-1927 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Federal Trade Commission Study - Publication Correspondence, 1924-1928 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - George Washington University - Immigration Laws (Memoranda and Correspondence), 1922-1932 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Historical Origin and Justification of Free Speech and of the Right to Petition - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Historical Origin and Justification of Free Speech and of the Right to Petition - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1940-1943 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Improvement of the Law of Future Interests in Land - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1922-1923 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Insurance Commissioners Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1921-1930 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, January-December, 1925 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1926-1929 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1930-1932 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1933-1934 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1935-1939 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Financial Data, 1925-1927 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Financial Data, 1928-1930 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission Study - Financial Data, 1931-1937 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Johns Hopkins University School of Jurisprudence - Reports, Correspondence, and Memoranda, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Modernizing Railway Accident Law (Appeal 779), February 1922 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Post Office Study - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Rule Making Power - Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda, 1926-1929 (Box 7, Folder 87)
    - Rule Making Power - Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda, 1930-1932 (Box 7, Folder 88)
    - Study of the Building Department of the City of New York - Correspondence, Finances and Memoranda, 1936-1943 (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - University of Chicago - Legislative Regulation (Memoranda, Correspondence, and Financial Data), 1928-1932 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - University of Chicago - Statutory Survey (Acknowledgements), May 12-31, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - University of Chicago - Statutory Survey (Acknowledgements), May 12-31, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - University of Chicago - Statutory Survey (Acknowledgements), June-December, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - University of Chicago - Statutory Survey (Editorial and General Correspondence), 1923-1926 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - University of Chicago - Statutory Survey (Editorial and General Correspondence), 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - University of Chicago Law School - Insanity as a Defense in Criminal Law (Correspondence and Financial Data), 1922-1923 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - University of Chicago Law School - Insanity as a Defense in Criminal Law (Correspondence and Financial Data), 1927-1931 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - University of Chicago Law School - Insanity as a Defense in Criminal Law (Correspondence and Financial Data), 1931-1933 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Workmen's Compensation Laws - Correspondence, Financial Data, Memoranda and Reports, 1928-1929 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Workmen's Compensation Laws - Correspondence, Financial Data, Memoranda and Reports, January-December, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Workmen's Compensation Laws - Correspondence, Financial Data, Memoranda and Reports, January-December, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Workmen's Compensation Laws - Correspondence, Financial Data, Memoranda and Reports, January-December, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Workmen's Compensation Laws - Correspondence, Financial Data, Memoranda and Reports, 1933-1934 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Workmen's Compensation Laws - Correspondence, Financial Data, Memoranda and Reports, 1935-1940 (Box 8, Folder 104)
    - Yale University - Woodbine's Edition of Bracton (Correspondence), 1929-1931 (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - International Law, 2
    - Harvard University Law School - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1927-1930 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Harvard University Law School - Minutes and Reports, 1928-1930 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Yale University - Correspondence, Memoranda and Reports, 1929-1930 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Law of Evidence, 3
    - Law of Evidence Study - Correspondence, Memoranda and Reports, 1921-1923 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Law of Evidence Study - Correspondence, Memoranda and Reports, 1924-1926 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Law of Evidence Study - Correspondence, Memoranda and Reports, 1927-1929 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Law of Evidence Study - Financial Data, 1922-1927 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Yale University School of Law - Sociopsychological Implications of Criminal Law (Correspondence, Memoranda and Reports), 1927-1930 (Box 8, Folder 113)